Finding Aid for J. Robert Willson Papers, 1933-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
J. Robert Willson Papers 1933-1993, 1964-1978
Willson, J. Robert (James Robert), 1912-
6 linear feet
85462 Aa 2
Professor of obstetrics and gynecology at the University of Michigan. Personal and professional correspondence, departmental records and annual reports, activities with professional associations, student notes, and materials dealing with abortion and family planning. Includes photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
J. Robert Willson (Donor no. 6740 ) donated his professional correspondence in 1983. The bulk of the collection was received from his wife in 1994.
The collection is open to research.
James Robert Willson, educator, physician, and specialist in obstetrics/gynecology, was born in Flint, Michigan, October 1, 1912, to Richard C. and Elizabeth S. Willson. He received his primary and secondary education in Flint. After attending Flint Junior College from 1930 to 1932, he transferred to the University of Michigan and completed his undergraduate degree in 1933. He enrolled in the University of Michigan Medical School and received the Doctor of Medicine degree in 1937.
He spent the next four years as an intern and resident in obstetrics and gynecology at the University of Michigan Hospital, completing residency in 1941. One year later he was awarded a Master of Science degree in obstetrics and gynecology from the University of Michigan, where he also served as an instructor in obstetrics and gynecology.
In 1942, he accepted a position at the University of Chicago as instructor and assistant professor at Chicago Lying-In Hospital. He left Chicago in 1946 to become professor and chairman of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology at Temple University School of Medicine in Philadelphia.
At Temple he assumed direction of a department that had no full-time faculty members. He recruited a nucleus of faculty member s and substantially reorganized the department, including redesigning medical student and resident education programs. He succeeded in making Temple's obstetrics and gynecology department the best in the city of Philadelphia, and one of the leading departments on the East Coast. While at Temple he was a member of the multi-disciplinary Unitarian Service Committee Medical Mission to Germany in 1950, and helped to revive the obstetrics and gynecology profession in Germany.
In 1963 he was asked to serve as a consultant to the University of Michigan obstetrics and gynecology search committee working to identify a successor to Dr. Norman F. Miller, who had announced his retirement after serving as chairman of the department since 1931. At the urging of the search committee, Willson was asked to become a candidate and was selected as the Bates Professor of Diseases of Women and Children, professor of Obstetrics/Gynecology, and chairman of the department beginning in 1964.
At Michigan he continued the same tradition of excellence that he had established at Temple University, developing a strong and outstanding department. Among his many contributions to the department was the expansion of the affiliated hospital program, an increase in the clinical faculty complement, and the development of the certified nurse-practitioner program.
Believing the ideal tenure for most chairmen to be between 10 and 15 years, Dr. Willson submitted his resignation as chairman in 1975. It was not until 1978, however, that his resignation was made official. He remained on the faculty as Bates Professor of Diseases of Women and Children, and professor of obstetrics and gynecology, serving in this capacity until his retirement in 1983, and as professor emeritus thereafter.
Despite his retirement and relocation to Albuquerque, New Mexico, he continued to remain active in his profession. In 1983 he was named adjunct professor in the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology at the University of New Mexico School of Medicine, and served as a member of the active staff of the University of New Mexico Hospital. He served in this capacity until his death on December 16, 1993. He was survived by his wife of 22 years, Joan Dunbar Staufer Willson.
Dr. Willson was a member of all of the distinguished societies within his profession. He was a founding member of the Society for Gynecological Investigation, served as director of the American Board of Obstetrics and Gynecology from 1964 to 1970, president of the Association of Professors of Gynecology and Obstetrics, 1965-1966, president of the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 1970-1971, president of the American Gynecological Society from 1979 to 1981, and was chairman of the Council on Resident Education in Obstetrics and Gynecology from 1967 to 1970. He was also active in numerous state and local societies.
An active contributor to scholarly literature, he was the author of more than 80 publications, and his textbook Obstetrics and Gynecology, first published in 1958, became a standard in the field. The ninth edition of this textbook was published in 1991.
The University of Michigan Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology Library was named in his honor in 1983, and he was honored with the creation of the J. Robert Willson Chair in Obstetrics-Gynecology at Temple University in 1994, the establishment of the J. Robert Willson Professorship in Obstetrics at the University of Michigan in 1989, and the J. Robert Willson Lectureship in Obstetrics and Gynecology at the University of New Mexico in 1993. He received the Distinguished Service Award from the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists in 1988, and the Distinguished Service Award from the Obstetrical Society of Philadelphia in 1992.
The papers of J. Robert Willson primarily document his long affiliation with the University of Michigan. The earliest material includes his student notes from Norman F. Miller's lectures on obstetrics and gynecology between 1933 and 1937. Documentation resumes with correspondence and departmental records documenting his tenure as chairman (1964-1978), and professor of obstetrics and gynecology (1964-1983).
The Willson papers are divided into seven records series: Correspondence; Biographical Material; Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology Files; Topical Files; Talks and Writings; Professional Societies and Organizations; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Abortion.; Family Planning Medical Services, Inc.; Gynecology.; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Obstetrics.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Obstetrics and Gynecology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School--Faculty.; Willson, J. Robert (James Robert), 1912-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Miller, Norman F.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Obstetrics and Gynecology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Willson, J. Robert (James Robert), 1912-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series dates from 1964 to 1993 and primarily represents the first installment of papers received from Dr. Willson, with one folder of correspondence dating from 1983 to 1993 added to this earlier accession. The correspondence is arranged into three parts: 1964-1967, 1968-1983, and 1983-1993. The bulk of the correspondence consists of professional and departmental correspondence, although there are a few personal letters scattered throughout the correspondence.
  - 1964-1967
    - A-D (Box 1)
    - F-L (Box 1)
    - M (Box 1)
    - N-Z (Box 1)
  - 1968-1983
    - A (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - C (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Clayon, Stanley; Cox, L.W.; Craig, M (Box 1)
    - D (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Dunn, Leo (Box 1)
    - E (Box 1)
    - F (Box 1)
    - G (Box 1)
    - H (Box 1)
    - I (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Iran, Universities in (Box 1)
    - J-K (Box 1)
    - L (Box 1)
    - M (Box 1)
    - N-P (Box 1)
    - Personal (Box 1)
    - R-S (Box 1)
    - T-V (Box 1)
    - W (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Walls, Linda L. (Box 1)
    - X-Z (Box 1)
  - 1983-1993
    - Chronological (Box 1)
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Material series includes copies of his curriculum vitae, clippings, and personnel related files detailing his tenure at the University of Michigan including his acceptance of the chairmanship, resignation and retirement. Of note is a detailed two-part autobiography written in 1992 that details his tenures at Temple University and at the University of Michigan. Most of the original sources drawn upon to compile the University of Michigan segment of his autobiography constitute the subsequent series.
  - Biographical (General) 1977-1993 (Box 2)
  - Book Burning Controversy 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Certificates and Awards 1939-1988 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Clippings, ca. 1963-1989 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae 1983, 1994 (Box 2)
  - "The Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology Temple University School of Medicine, January 1947-December 1963," 1992 (Box 2)
  - "The Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology: The University of Michigan Medical School, 1964-1978," 1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Personnel (University of Michigan)
    - Acceptance of Chairmanship 1962-1964 (Box 2)
    - General 1963-1978 (Box 2)
    - Resignation as Chairman 1975, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Retirement 1982-1983 (Box 2)
- Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology Files
  The Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology Files constitute documents utilized by Willson in the preparation of his 1992 account, "The Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology the University of Michigan Medical School, 1964-1978." These files richly illustrate his work at Michigan and include a nearly complete run of annual reports from 1959 to 1978, a 1963 departmental evaluation, staff meeting minutes, 1971-1976, and departmental advisory committee records. The affiliated hospital program is well documented as is the planning and development of the Holden Perinatal Research Unit. The development of the nurse-midwife and nurse-practitioner programs are also well chronicled, including extensive background files. An interesting sidelight is the 1972 correspondence regarding Sara Ethel Laws who was reportedly the first African-American child born in University Hospital in 1892.
  - Affiliated Hospitals
    - Administrative Files
      - General 1969-1972 (Box 2)
      - Basic Science Course 1972-1976 (Box 2)
      - Clinical Clerkships 1971-1972, 1976 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee 1971-1973 (Box 2)
      - Minutes of Affiliated Hospitals in Obstetrics and Gynecology 1965-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Obstetrics/Gynecology Planning Board 1968-1970 (Box 2)
    - Affiliated Hospitals
      - Beyer Memorial Hospital (Ypsilanti) Obstetrical Study Group 1973 (Box 2)
      - Blodgett Memorial Hospital (Grand Rapids) 1966-1972 (Box 2)
      - Grand Rapids-Kalamazoo Liaison Committee 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Henry Ford Hospital (Detroit) 1967-1977 (Box 2)
      - Pontiac General Hospital 1965-1969 (Box 2)
      - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital (Ann Arbor) 1967-1971, 4 folders
        - Interdepartmental Meetings 1972-1974 (Box 2)
        - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital-University of Michigan Obstetrical Study Committee 1972 (Box 2)
      - Wayne County General Hospital 1960-1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1959 (Box 3)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    - 1964 (Box 3)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 3)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - 1973 (Box 3)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - 1974 (Box 3)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - 1975 (Box 3)
    - 1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Birthing Room in Women's Hospital, Ad Hoc Group Considering 1977 (Box 3)
  - Cesarean Section 1975-1977 (Box 3)
  - Dean of the Medical School 1966-1977 (Box 3)
  - Deanship Review (Box 3)
    (see: Review Committee of the Medical School)
  - Departmental Advisory Committee 1973-1975, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Departmental Attitude Toward Women 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - Departmental Development (Long Range Planning and Development) 1967-1972 (Box 3)
  - Departmental Evaluation 1963
    - Supplement (Lectures and Demonstrations) 1963 (Box 3)
  - Departmental Procedures and Regulations 1972-1974 (Box 3)
  - Education Committee 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    (includes minutes)
  - Executive Committee (Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology) 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Fetal Research 1975-1977 (Box 3)
  - Gynecological Clinic Relocation Committee 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Gynecology Service Move to Main Hospital 1968-1973 (Box 3)
  - Holden Perinatal Research Unit
    - Proposals and Planning 1963-1965, 1969-1977 (Box 3)
    - Progress and Dedication 1969-1975 (Box 3)
    - Publicity 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation Perinatal Center Proposal 1974 (Box 3)
  - Home Birthing 1977 (Box 3)
  - House Officer Consultation 1972-1977 (Box 3)
  - Laws, Sara Ethel ("First Negro Child Born in University Hospital, 1892") 1972 (Box 4)
  - Maternal and Child Health Program 1969 (Box 4)
  - Nurse-Midwifery
    - Background Articles 1973-1981 (Box 4)
    - General 1967, 1971-1977, 1980 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan 1972-1984, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Nurse-Practitioner Program 1970-1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Obstetric Intensive Care Unit 1975-1978 (Box 4)
  - Obstetric Service 1978, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Obstetrics-Gynecology Accelerated Residency Program 1969-1974 (Box 4)
  - Obstetrics-Gynecology Staff Meeting Minutes 1971-1976, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Oncology Training Program 1971-1973, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Outpatient Operating Facilities
    - General 1969-1977 (Box 4)
    - Gynecology Outpatient Department 1969-1976 (Box 4)
    - Obstetrics Outpatient Service 1971-1978 (Box 4)
  - Periodic Health Appraisal Unit (Pelvic Exams) 1973-1977 (Box 4)
  - Population (Reproduction) Research Center 1975-1978 (Box 4)
  - Professional Fee Plan 1966-1974 (Box 4)
  - Psychiatric Consultation-Liaison 1969-1977 (Box 4)
  - Reproductive Endocrinology
    - Clippings 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Infertility Service 1975 (Box 4)
    - Sheep Research Facility 1975 (Box 4)
  - Resident-Staff Conferences, ca. 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Review Committee of the Medical School 1977 (Box 4)
  - Self-Medication by Postpartum Patients 1965-1966, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Sexual Assault Treatment Center 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Student Health Service Obstetric-Gynecology Consultation 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Three Year Curriculum Subcommittee 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Ultrasound 1970-1978 (Box 4)
  - Women's Hospital
    - Dermatology Service Relocation 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Renovations 1964-1978, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Ypsilanti Prenatal Clinic 1971-1975 (Box 4)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files relate primarily to the topics of abortion and family planning, but also include Willson's student notes from medical school (1933-1937), brochures on the Unitarian Service Committee Medical Mission to Germany in 1950, and reports and correspondence from his 1973 sabbatical leave. The background files on abortion include position statements, clippings, and information on therapeutic abortions at the University of Michigan. The files of the Family Planning Medical Services, Inc., include bylaws, minutes, and other planning material relating to the development of this family planning center for Washtenaw County.
  - Abortion
    - Background 1956-1970, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Background Publications 1976, 1983-1993 (Box 5)
    - Belous Case (People v. Belous, California Supreme Court) 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - Clippings 1967-1969 (Box 5)
    - Conference on Planning for Abortion Facilities in Michigan 1971 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Abortion Bill 1965-1967 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Council for the Study of Abortions 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Society of Obstetricians and Gynecologists Committee on Therapeutic Abortions 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - Therapeutic Abortions at the University of Michigan 1969-1975 (Box 5)
  - Family Planning Medical Services, Inc.
    - Articles of Incorporation, By-Laws, Board of Directors 1972-1973 (Box 5)
    - Abortion Background 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - General 1972 (Box 5)
  - Hyperbaric Pressure Research 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Litigation
    - Harrison et al. vs. Willson et al. 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - Lazar vs. Willson 1981 (Box 5)
  - Sabbatical Leave Report: "Non-Physician Health Care and Family Planning," August-November 1973, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Student Notes, Obstetrics and Gynecology, ca. 1933-1937, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Taiwan-Family Planning Health Program 1965-1966, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Tokyo Maternity Clinic 1968-1968 (Box 5)
  - Unitarian Service Committee Medical Mission to Germany (Pamphlets) 1950 (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw Young Mothers Project 1967-1970 (Box 5)
- Talks and Writings
  The Talks and Writing Series includes sixteen outlines and presentations relating to various issues within the practice of obstetrics and gynecology. A folder of published offprints is also included here, which gives evidence of the scope of his research and writing.
  - Unpublished Talks and Writings
    - Additional Certification Within Obstetrics-Gynecology Objectives undated (Box 5)
    - Corporate Responsibility for Medical Education 1971 (Box 5)
    - The Education of the Obstetrician-Gynecologist 1967 (Box 5)
    - The Effect of Consumerism on Obstetric Gynecology Practice 1983 (Box 5)
    - Ethical Dilemmas in Obstetrics 1972 (Box 5)
    - Ethical Issues in Fetal Therapy 1985 (Box 5)
    - The Expansion of Preventive Health Measures for Women: The Role of the Physician 1967 (Box 5)
    - Intrauterine Contraceptive Devices: Practical Considerations in Their Use undated (Box 5)
    - Issues in Obstetrics for Consumer and Professional 1979 (Box 5)
    - Obstetrics-Gynecology in A Changing World 1965 (Box 5)
    - Obstetrics-Gynecology: Progress and Problems 1981 (Box 5)
    - Philadelphia 1976 (Box 5)
    - Recruitment-A Realistic Approach 1973 (Box 5)
    - What's New in Obstetrics-Gynecology 1985 (Box 5)
    - What is the Place of Intrauterine Contraceptive Devices for Family Planning undated (Box 5)
    - Where Have We been (Outline) 1979 (Box 5)
  - Offprints 1962-1983 (Box 5)
- Professional Societies and Organizations
  Professional Societies and Organizations provides an outline of Willson's involvement in national, state and local professional societies. Although several national organizations are represented, the records are strongest for the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, which includes his term as president (1970-1971), and work with the Commission on Health Care for Women, and the Council on Resident Education in Obstetrics and Gynecology. The file for the Norman F. Miller Gynecologic Society contains information on the society as well as on Miller himself.
  - American Board of Obstetrics and Gynecology 1980 (Box 6)
  - American College of Nurse Midwives 1970-1972 (Box 6)
  - American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (ACOG)
    - Presidential Records
      - General 1968-1971 (Box 6)
      - Proceedings-Executive Committee Post Annual Clinical Meeting April 17, 1970 (Box 6)
      - Publications 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Commission on Health Care for Women 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Council on Resident Education in Obstetrics and Gynecology (CREOG) 1967-1977 (Box 6)
    - "Prolonged and Abnormal Labor," 1977, audio cassette tape (Box 6)
  - American Gynecologic and Obstetrical Society
    - Amalgamation 1980 (Box 6)
    - General 1981-1983 (Box 6)
  - American Gynecologic Society 1961, 1965-1968, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Deutsche Gesellschaft fur Gynakologie und Geburtshilfe 1979-1980, 1986, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Norman F. Miller Gynecologic Society 1956-1987 (scattered) (Box 6)
  - Society for Gynecologic Investigation 1983 (Box 6)
  - Washtenaw Obstetrical-Gynecologic Society 1965-1970, 1985 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes portraits of Willson, his predecessor and mentor, Norman F. Miller, the Norman F. Miller Gynecologic Society, as well as group photographs of faculty and staff groups, professional groups, and snapshots relating to hyperbaric pressure research.
  - Hyperbaric Research, ca. 1982 (Box 6)
  - Norman F. Miller 1943, 1957 ca. 1963 (Box 6)
  - Norman F. Miller Gynecological Society 1964-1972 (Box 6)
  - Obstetrics and Gynecology Faculty and Staff Groups, 1964/1965- 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Professional Groups 1965-1992 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - J. Robert Willson Portraits 1969-1990 (Box 6)
Related Material
For related record groups within the Bentley Historical Library, researchers are advised to consult the records of the University of Michigan Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Michigan Medical School Records, and University of Michigan School of Nursing Records. A segment of the Willson papers, primarily relating to his tenure at Temple University, is housed in the College of Physicians archives and library in Philadelphia.